Sir.
先生
May I ask
先生にお伺いします
if can you cure blood stasis?
血瘀の症は治せますか
If Xiao Wuyi dies,
蕭無衣は死んだ
you can take back the military power he holds.
兵権を手に入れる好機だというのに
Why bother to save his life?
なぜ助けるのです
I just want to defeat him,
奴は私の手で打ち負かしたい
not to let him perish at my hands.
私の手で死なせたくはない
I can save him.
助けることはできます
But if saving him
ですが奴を助けることで
is at the cost of others' lives,
より多くの者が死ぬとしたら
can you bear the weight of such a sin?
その罪を背負えますか
Yes.
背負えます
I once saved your life.
かつて先生の命を救いました
In return, you promised to save three people for me.
その時 ３つの命を救うと約束されました
The first one...
一つ目は
was the young emperor.
皇帝の若造の命を守れと
I did save him.
お約束は果たしました
He is still alive now.
今もまだ生きております
Then the second person
では二つ目
I'm asking you to save is Xiao Wuyi.
蕭無衣を助けていただきたい
It never crossed my mind
助けてくれるとは
that you would help me.
思いませんでした
I believe...
きっと
Mother would also agree to let me do this.
母上もそうすることを望んでくださるはず
Right.
はい
Neither did I expect
私も思わなかった
Xiao Wuyi to put righteousness above family,
蕭無衣が身内を犠牲に大義を貫き
reopen the An-Lu case,
安陸の汚名をそそぎ
and even tell the whole world
天下に
that Crown Prince Wenxi is dead,
文熹太子は死んだと知らせ
thus leaving himself no way out.
己の退路を断つとは
It seems he really
どうやら
doesn't care about that position.
奴は本気で気にしていないようだ
All the people in this world pray for
天下の民が求めているのは
nothing but peace and happiness.
平和な暮らしだけ
Who cares if the throne is made
玉座が金でできていようが
of gold or bronze?
銅でできていようが誰も気にしません
I truly look forward to the Ye
蕭無衣が築こうとしている大鄴を
that Xiao Wuyi tries to build,
私は期待したいし
and I'm glad to help him with it.
実現も手伝いたい
Yaoyao.
夭夭
As your father, I...
この父は
I did much wrongdoing in the past.
過去に多くの過ちを犯した
I must apologize to you.
すまなかった
I am so sorry.
許してくれ
It's cold and harsh in the Northern Border.
北境は寒さが厳しい
Do take care
よいか
to stay warm.
厚着を忘れるな
Fuhua,
甫華
you had a good daughter.
いい娘さんを持ったな
His Majesty has agreed to establish the spring exam as a regular system.
陛下は春考の常制化をお認めになり
The Grand Tutor has also submitted his resignation.
太傅も辞表を提出されました
You beat me once again.
またお前の勝ちか
When will you go back to the Northern Border?
北境にはいつ戻る
I've petitioned His Majesty for leave
陛下に願い出て
to first inspect the capital's defense in three days before heading back
三日後に都の防備を巡察し
to the Northern Border.
その後 北境へ戻る
The Eagle King's troops have been making moves.
鷹王の部隊に不穏な動きがある
I need to get back soon.
早く戻らねば
Now, I'm thinking
今 思うのだが
that you're about to die,
お前はもうすぐ死ぬ
but there is still so much time left
だが私と謝嘉魚の人生は
in my life and Xie Jiayu's life.
まだ長い
Anything could happen.
これから何が起きるか分からん
So,
だから
there shouldn't be rush.
急ぐことはない
The mystery of mineral deposits within the Phoenix Heart Token
雀骨令に隠された鉱床の秘密は
has been cracked by Xie Jiayu.
謝嘉魚が解き明かした
If the court needs them in the future,
今後 朝廷が鉱床を必要とすれば
she'll tell you where they are.
彼女がお教えするでしょう
With Xie Jiayu around,
謝嘉魚がいれば
this token
この令牌など
is no longer useful.
もはや無用だ
Xiao Wuyi!
蕭無衣
"When the Phoenix Heart Token appears, peace shall be restored in the world."
雀骨出でて 天下定まる
You didn't hesitate to destroy
誰もが欲しがるものを
what others yearn for.
お前はあっさりと壊す
By replacing the token with Xie Jiayu,
令をもって人を化す
you're trying to make sure no one can hurt her
それは お前の生前も死後も
whether you are alive or dead,
謝嘉魚に誰も手出しできぬようにするため
not even me.
私でさえもな
You devised a thorough plan
そこまで周到に計画し
and gave up everything,
すべてを捨てておきながら
yet in the final days of your life,
命尽きる間際に
you chose to leave her and go to war.
彼女を置いて出征するとは
Xiao Wuyi, what on earth
蕭無衣 お前にとって
matters most
最も重要なのは
to you?
いったい何だ
Please don't die too soon.
すぐに死ぬなよ
I will surely beat you once.
必ず一度はお前に勝ってみせる
Xiao Wuyi!
蕭無衣
Li Mao has gone back to the palace.
李茂が帰ったわ
Let's go home, too.
私たちも帰りましょう
Why is it broken?
なぜ割れたの
This is the Phoenix Heart Token.
これは雀骨令よ
You already know it by heart, don't you?
とっくに頭に入っているだろうに
What use does it have now?
今さら必要ない
Besides,
それに
it was originally my mother's Phoenix Imperial Seal.
これはもともと母后の鳳印だ
How about we melt it and cast it
溶かして作り直し
into a hairpin for you?
そなたのかんざしにするのはどうだ
Yuanji, you're so full of surprises.
姉上は本当にすごいです
You got the first place in the exam in just one try.
一気に首席になられるなんて
I thought the most nervous moment of my life would be the day
私が生涯で最も緊張するのは
I married into Prince Jing'an's Mansion.
靖安王府に嫁ぐ日だと思っていました
Little did I expect
ですが まさか
to feel even more nervous now than that day.
今日がその日以上に胸が高鳴るとは
That said, I've never been so clear
けれど今日ほど
about my goal as I am today.
自分が何をしたいのかはっきりと分かった日はありません
But I'm a bit worried about your identity.
ただ姉上の身分が心配で
If Mao ever...
もし阿茂が生きていたら
Yaoyao, you're worried about nothing.
夭夭 心配しすぎよ
Prince Qi
岐王は
was even more eager than I was about the exam results.
私以上にこの春の試験の結果を期待しているわ
Since he didn't expose my identity,
私を暴かなかった以上
I'm sure he won't either in the future.
今後もそうしない
Only when he has some kind of hold on me
私の弱みを握ってこそ
will he feel more at ease using me.
安心して私を使えるの
I deem it as a blessing for me to marry into the Xiao family,
蕭家に嫁ぎ 皆様の家族となって
to become part of the household,
支え合えるのは
♪ Half by choice, half washed away ♪
私の幸せです
You'll be embraced by the vast world.
それはどこまでも広がる青空と海のよう
I wish you
あなた様の
all the best,
すべてが順調で
and may all your dreams come true.
願いがかないますように
Where are you going, Darling?
奥方様 どちらへ
Three years ago,
３年前
you fled to Northern Qin
奥方は北秦へ逃亡し
and begged me for shelter,
我に庇護を求めてきたな
saying that you offended Xiao Wuyi
蕭無衣の怒りを買い
and even your brother, the Regent, couldn't protect you,
監国の兄君でさえかばいきれず
so you were driven out of Southern Ye
南鄴から追い出され
to fend for yourself.
見捨てられたと
What now?
何だ
You want to return to your homeland?
今になって故郷へ戻りたいとは
Do you not fear death anymore?
もう死ぬのは怖くなくなったか
Isn't there a saying in Southern Ye?
南鄴にはこういう言葉があるだろう
That is, "Once a couple, always a bond."
一夜の契りは百夜の契り
Can you really bear to leave me behind?
我を捨てられるのか
Don't you forget
忘れるなよ
that I've never intercepted a single letter
この数年 そなたが上京で情報を集め
you've sent to Jiankang in secret
剣慷へ密かに送っていた書状を
after collecting intelligence in the Capital.
我は一通も止めなかった
What discontent can you possibly have?
何か不満でも
So you've been using me.
ずっと私を利用していたのね
All you've done is for today, right?
すべてはこの日のため
I just presented
私は そなたの兄に
a great opportunity to your brother.
絶好の機会を与えたのだ
You should be thanking me.
むしろ私に感謝すべきだぞ
For that injustice from over 20 years ago,
20年以上も前の冤罪だ
it is time to put an end to it.
決着をつけるべきだろう
After all, your brother is a descendant of the Xie family, isn't he?
そなたの兄君も謝家の子孫ではないか
Guards!
誰かいるか
Take her away.
この者を連れていけ
-Yes.
はっ
By order of the Heir's Consort,
世子妃様のご命令です
Your Highness must not strain your eyes anymore.
これ以上 目をお使いになりませぬよう
You think you run the place,
後ろ盾ができたからと
now that someone's backing you up?
随分と羽振りがいいようだな
I'm just following orders.
私は命令に従っているまでです
If Your Highness is angry,
お怒りでしたら
take it out on Her Highness.
世子妃様に当たりなされ
It's noticeable in this inspection of the capital's defense
この度の京畿の防備巡察により
that the Imperial Guard's combat power has improved.
禁軍の戦力は向上し
The reform has proven effective,
制度改革は大きな成果を上げ
and removed the potential risks of the Northern Expedition.
北伐の憂いもなくなりました
Why are you still worried, Your Highness?
世子様は なぜまだご心配なのですか
I don't like war,
戦は好まぬ
but peace can't be restored without it.
だが戦でなければ平定できぬ
Whether a nation prospers or falls,
国が興ろうが滅びようが
it is always the people who suffer.
苦しむのは民だ
From now on, you are no longer registered as a slave,
これからは奴婢の身分ではなく
but the manager of the Miraculous Craft.
妙手の差配人となるのよ
I'm leaving you to handle everything
この剣慷のすべてを
I have in Jiankang.
あなたに任せるわ
Ever since Cang'er's passing,
蒼耳さんが亡くなってから
I've been considering your placement.
ずっとあなたの身の振り方を考えていたの
Good thing you didn't fall in love with Qing Long.
青龍を気に入らなくてよかったわ
Otherwise, I would be worried
もしも嫁がせる相手が
if I had to marry you to a man who could
いつ戦場に行くか分からない人だったら
get on the battlefield anytime.
安心できないもの
There's no way I'd be into him.
あの方を好きになるわけないでしょう
But I can see he clings to you all the time.
でも いつもあなたに付きまとっているように見えるけど
He's not clinging to me.
私に付きまとっているのではなく
He's clearly trying to spend
私を通して
more time with Yan Yue through me.
偃月姉様に付きまとっているのです
Then what about you?
じゃあ あなたは
I also love being around with Yan Yue, of course.
もちろん私も偃月姉様とご一緒したいだけです
In my heart,
この南星にとって
Your Highness
一番大切なのは
is the most important.
お嬢様だけです
I wish to stick with you, My Lady.
南星は お嬢様と離れたくありません
You silly girl.
おばかさんね 南星
I just entrusted you
私の最後の逃げ道を
with my biggest fallback.
あなたに託したのよ
You're highly talented in business and accounting.
あなたには商いと帳簿の才能があるわ
Both warfare
戦も
and weapon manufacturing
軍械作りも
cost a great deal of money.
とてもお金がかかるものだから
If I am short of money in the future
もし将来お金に困って
and write to you for help,
手紙を書いたら
you must not pretend not to see it.
見なかったふりなんて絶対にしないでね
I swear, My Lady,
南星は誓います
to manage the Miraculous Craft well
必ずお嬢様のため 妙手を立派に切り盛りし
and make more money for you.
もっとたくさんのお金を稼ぎます
Master, are you sure about sending all these books
ご当主様 本当にこれらの書物を
to the Imperial Academy?
すべて太学へお送りになるのですか
You've gone to
これらはご当主様が
great lengths to collect them all your life.
一生をかけて苦労して集められたものでは
Now that I'm letting things go,
手放すと決めたからには
I might as well do it all the way.
いっそきれいさっぱりと
Master, do you really think
ご当主様は本気で
His Highness chose the correct path?
殿下の道が正しいとお信じですか
Jiayu...
嘉魚
Yaoyao said something right.
夭夭さんの言ったことに一理ある
Each generation has its own path to walk.
世代には世代の進むべき道がある
Now, Yizhi is sure to ascend the throne.
今や易之の儲君の位は盤石だ
Although the path he will take
彼が将来歩む道が
may not be correct,
正しいとは限らぬ
sticking to old patterns is surely wrong.
だが古い道を守り続けるのは間違いなく誤りだ
As for us...
我々はな
As for us old folks,
我々のような老いぼれは
it's time we made way for them.
そろそろ彼らに道を譲る時だ
Grand Tutor!
太傅様
Can you really bear to leave Jiankang?
本当に剣慷を離れるおつもりか
Prince Jing'an?
靖安王
Are you really going to
太傅様は
let me and my family off the hook so easily?
このまま靖安王府を見逃すおつもりか
What do you mean?
どういう意味だ
I wrote
これは わしが
this confession to Empress Wenxi myself.
自ら文熹皇后のために書いた罪状書だ
Grand Tutor, don't you want to know
太傅様は知りたくないとでも
who orchestrated
あの冤罪事件の
that injustice
黒幕が一体誰だったのか
from years ago?
仕組まれたことか
Aren't you...
あなたは
Master!
家主では
Someone come here!
誰かおらぬか
How odd. Why is no one around?
おかしいわ なぜ誰もいないの
Mother!
母上
Ruisheng!
蕊生姉様
Father!
父上
Did Father go out for drinks and gambling again?
父上は また酒を飲んで博打を
Prince Qi invites Your Highness
岐王殿下が世子妃様を
to the Grand Tutor's Mansion.
太傅府へお呼びです
Yaoyao.
夭夭
Please don't cry when you see the Grand Tutor later.
後で太傅にお会いしても 泣くんじゃないわよ
Though he had selfish motives before,
あの方に下心はあったけれど
he did spend 18 years raising you.
18年間あなたを育ててくださったのよ
Death wipes away all wrongs.
亡くなったのだから
So don't hate him anymore.
恨むのはおよしなさい
♪ So desolate ♪
これは夭夭が父上のために
on my own specifically
手ずから磨いた黒玉の指輪です
as a birthday gift to you, Father.
誕生日の贈り物として
What do you think?
いかがですか 父上
Is it pretty?
お気に召しましたか
Yes.
うむ
So pretty.
実にすばらしい
I'll keep it on all the time,
父はいつでもこれを身に着け
and think of my dearest Yaoyao all the time.
いつでも私の夭夭を思っているぞ
Great.
はい
Father...
父上
The chapter of Jade Algae in the Book of Rites says:
『礼記・玉藻』にこうある
"Keep the voice calm, the head upright, and the bearing dignified."
声は静かに 頭はまっすぐに 気は厳かにと
Do you remember what it means?
その意味を覚えておるか
A person of virtue should
君子の振る舞いは
behave and speak with composure,
言葉は穏やかに
holding his or her head high when walking and sitting.
胸を張ってまっすぐに座るべし
Father,
父上
sorry for losing my manners just now.
先ほどは失礼いたしました
If you were not my daughter,
もしお前が私の娘でなければ
you could have
そなたの人生は
led a freer life.
もっと自由であったろう
Father...
父上
How did this happen?
どうしてこんなことに
What exactly was going on?
一体 何があったのですか
Wasn't he preparing to retire
あの方はもう
and return to his hometown?
官職を辞して故郷に帰るのでは
Who on earth did this?
一体誰の仕業なのですか
It was Xiao Ju.
蕭駒だ
What?
なんですって
That's impossible.
あり得ません
The Commandant of Justice and the common people witnessed it.
廷尉と民がこの目で見ており
Xiao Ju
犯人も
was caught on the spot.
その場で捕らえられた
Your Highness!
殿下
Say what happened.
そなたが話せ
Yes, Your Highness.
はっ 殿下
Heir's Consort,
世子妃様
today, I heard someone causing trouble in the Grand Tutor's Mansion,
臣は本日 太傅府で騒ぎがあったと聞き
so I came.
駆けつけましたところ
Then I ran right into Prince Jing'an committing a murder here.
靖安王が凶行に及んでおりました
Who are you?
誰ですって
Prince Jing'an?
靖安王です
He slashed at everyone he saw as he moved.
彼は道中 手当たり次第に人を斬りつけ
All the people on this very street can testify
街中の民が証人です
that the assailant was exactly Prince Jing'an, Xiao Ju.
犯人はまさしく靖安王 蕭駒です
Suddenly, a cart dashed in
突然一台の荷車が
and knocked the fleeing Prince Jing'an down.
逃亡中の靖安王をはね飛ばし
Only then was he captured.
捕らえることができました
All of this seems unreasonable.
道理に合いません
If Prince Jing'an wanted revenge
もし父上が 私の父と
for knowing my father
柳昭林の共謀を知り
had conspired with Liu Zhaolin,
報復の機をうかがっていたなら
he wouldn't have chosen to do it in broad daylight,
白昼堂々犯行に及ぶはずがない
gone out to the street instead of small alleys
人に見られても裏道を使わず
upon being discovered, or slashed at others.
さらに数人を斬るなんて
Wasn't it practically finding witnesses for himself?
自ら証人を作っているようなものです
I was also confused,
私も疑問でした
till I found this in the Grand Tutor's arms.
太傅の懐からこれを見つけるまでは
This is...
これは
a confession letter Prince Jing'an wrote to Empress Wenxi years ago.
父上がかつて文熹皇后に下した罪の詔勅
This confession letter
この詔勅は
is dated the 12th year of the Zhaoning reign,
署名が昭寧12年で
exactly on the eve of the Capital's fall.
まさしく上京陥落の前夜のものです
Back then, Prince Jing'an was well aware
かつて靖安王は
that the An and Lu families were falsely accused,
安陸の二氏が無実と知りつつ
yet he still brought these 200-odd people onto the execution ground.
200人余りを刑場へ送りました
So, when Prince Jing'an learned
では王爺が
that this letter was in the Grand Tutor's hands,
この書状が太傅の手に渡ったと知り
he killed the latter to silence him.
口封じで殺害した
This makes perfect sense.
というのも筋が通ります
It's not right.
違う
My father figured out long ago that the An and Lu families were wronged.
父上は安陸二氏の無実をとうに知っていた
If he had known about this letter,
この書状の存在を知っていたなら
he wouldn't have kept silent for so long.
今日まで黙ってはいないはず
When the Capital fell,
上京の陥落
if this letter wasn't ruined at war,
もし書状が戦火で焼けず
then it must've gone to Northern Qin...
北秦の手に渡ったとしたら…
Right.
そうだ
It's Northern Qin.
北秦だ
Commandant,
廷尉
did you see Prince Jing'an speak at that time?
その者が話すのを直接見ましたか
No, he didn't.
見ておりません
That explains it.
やはりな
One's accent gives away one's identity.
訛りで身元が割れてしまうからだ
Mao, do you remember Cui Jun?
阿茂 崔浚を覚えているか
He used the secret disguise technique of Northern Qin.
あれは北秦の変装の秘術だ
This is all a conspiracy by Northern Qin.
すべて北秦の陰謀だ
Your Highness...
殿下
Who had the audacity to tie me up?
何やつだ この余を縛るとは
Untie me now!
縄を解け
Prince Jing'an,
靖安王
what do you have to say?
何か言うことはあるか
I...
私は
was on my way home after gambling
博打の後 帰宅する途中で
when someone attacked me.
何者かに襲われ
Then I woke up and found myself here
その後は何も覚えていません
without knowing anything.
気づいたらここに
Your Highness,
殿下に申し上げます
Anfeng Restaurant,
安鳳酒楼
Laowang Temple,
老王廟
Su's Rouge Shop, and four other
蘇記の紅屋など７か所の
spy outposts of Northern Qin
北秦の密偵の拠点は
have all been investigated.
全て調査を終えました
The Northern Qin spies are working as normal,
北秦の密偵は普段どおりで
showing no suspicious activity.
何の異変もありません
Neither has anyone withdrawn.
撤退した者もおりません
If this was really the work of Northern Qin spies,
これが北秦の密偵の仕業なら
logically speaking, whether it was a success or a failure,
理屈では成功しようが失敗しようが
they would've withdrawn instantly.
すぐに撤退するはず
But they didn't leave.
だが連中は動かない
They must have no knowledge of this, since they wouldn't
本当に何も知らないのでなければ
just wait to be rounded up all at once, right?
一網打尽にされるのを待つつもりか
Prince Jing'an,
靖安王
you said someone attacked you.
襲われたと言うが
Was there a witness?
証人はいるか
Probably...
多分
no.
いません
When I go gambling,
博打は
I always do it behind my wife's back.
妻には内緒で行っておりました
But Jiayu knows it.
嘉魚は知っています
Is the content of this confession letter true?
では この詔勅に書かれていることは真実か
Back then, in order to...
かつて
suppress the noble families,
名家を抑えるため
I...
臣は
didn't reveal the truth, indeed.
確かに冤罪を明らかにしませんでした
Given that justice has been restored for the An and Lu families...
安陸二氏の冤罪はすでに晴らされた以上
Guards!
誰か
-Yes!
はっ
Detain everyone in Prince Jing'an's Mansion,
靖安王府の者を全員拘束
and have Xiao Yao arrested and brought back from Yingzhou immediately.
直ちに人を郢州へ遣わし 蕭堯を捕らえ
Strip him of his post there as well.
その場で解任せよ
Yes.
はっ
Your Highness...
殿下
The detention will be in secret.
秘密裏に拘束せよ
Your Highness, this...
殿下 これは…
This...
蕭無衣は
Xiao Wuyi hasn't returned from the inspection tour yet.
まだ巡察から戻っておらぬ
All that has happened here must be kept secret
事前に気づかせるな
from him, in case he flees.
逃がすな
Escort the Heir's Consort into the palace.
世子妃を宮中へ
Take her away!
連れて行け
Shouldn't you say something?
何か言うことはないのか
What should I say?
何を言えばいいの
Mock me, scold me, throw
喜んだり怒ったり
a tantrum or threaten me.
わめき散らし 脅すのもいい
Anything is fine.
何でもいい
Just do what you used to.
昔のおまえのままでいてくれ
Time passes like a flowing river.
時は流れゆくもの
How can you expect things to remain the same?
過去には戻れません
Did I turn you into this?
俺がおまえをこう変えたのか
You knew my father's death was suspicious in many ways,
父上の死は不審な点が多く
and that Prince Jing'an was framed by Northern Qin.
靖安王も北秦の罠だと知りながら
But you still seized on it to stir up more trouble.
これを口実にするのですね
How I wish you were angry
少しでも
partly because of me.
俺のためであってほしかった
I thought after the spring examination,
春の試験の後
you and Xiao Wuyi had reconciled.
おまえと蕭無衣は和解したとばかり
But I'm also afraid you'd only remember the bad things about me.
でも 私の悪い面しか覚えていないのではと
You believe Xiao Wuyi has never coveted power,
蕭無衣が権力を望まぬと信じ
and you've obtained the Phoenix Heart Token.
雀骨令も手に入れた
He can't prove he is Crown Prince Wenxi by any means.
文熹太子だと証明する術もない
Besides...
それに
he can't live for much longer anyway.
どうせ長くは生きられぬ
Don't you resent him for dragging you down
長くない彼を恨みもせず
as his days are numbered?
道連れにされるというの
No one can drag me down.
誰にも道連れにはされません
I willingly chose to stick with him.
自分の意志で彼と共に歩むのです
Then if he leaves you forever,
では 彼がおまえを捨てたら
what will you do?
どうする
As long as he has never let me down,
彼が私を裏切らない限り
even if he is gone forever,
たとえ亡くなっても
I'll still feel like he's around.
私と共にいます
I'll carry on his legacy
彼の分まで
and live my life well.
しっかり生きていきます
Does it mean you left me back then
では あの時 俺から離れたのは
because I somehow let you down?
俺に失望したからか
I just couldn't understand you,
ただ あなたが分からなかった
like now—
今と同じで
I still can't tell
今もまだ見抜けません
when you are acting
いつが芝居で
and when you are being genuine.
いつが本心なのか
Maybe
おそらく
you really are suited to be an emperor.
あなたは本当に帝王に向いているわ
Unpredictable.
喜怒が読めず
Calculated like a sovereign.
その帝王の術は
How very fearful.
人に恐怖を抱かせます
Officers,
お役人様
I'm terribly sorry.
すみません
I'll go right away.
すぐに失礼します
Are you alright?
大丈夫か
You keep me in chains yet protect me.
私を縛りながら守るなんて
Mao,
阿茂
you're such a contradiction.
矛盾しているわ
I remember you're allergic to peaches.
桃は苦手だったわよね
Never did I imagine that one day,
まさか
I'd have no choice but to attack you.
あなたに手を下す日が来るとは
Freeze!
逃げるな
As you said,
あなたの言うとおりだ
Prince Qi knew that Northern Qin
殿下は北秦が
plotted to turn a ruler against his ministers,
君臣を裂こうと
yet he still capitalized on it to seize
知りながら それを口実に
Prince Jing'an's military power.
靖安王府の兵権を奪うおつもりだ
So he just faked his previous alliance with Wuyi...
では 無衣さんへの態度は芝居だったのですね
Right now, I have no idea
今となっては
if he's being genuine or pretending.
彼の本心が分かりません
The priority
何より
is to have Xiao Wuyi found
まず蕭無衣さんを見つけ出し
and warned not to come back to Jiankang
剣慷へは決して戻らせぬことです
so he won't fall into this trap.
罠にはまります
You're right.
あなたの言うとおりね
A man is judged by his actions, not his thoughts,
君子は行いを論じ 心は論ぜず
let alone a sovereign.
ましてや帝王はなおさらです
I'm afraid only I can
今となっては
speak up for the Xiao family now.
蕭家を弁護できるのは私しかおりません
I'll submit a memorial tomorrow.
明日 上奏します
Don't, Yuanji.
いけません 姉上
Or you'll irritate Prince Qi.
それでは岐王を怒らせてしまいます
An official must be loyal,
忠義を尽くすも
but not blindly loyal.
愚忠にはあたりません
If there are so many doubts about this case,
この件に本当に疑点が多いのなら
then it is my duty to submit a memorial on it.
上奏するのが私の責任です
You stay here for the night.
今夜はひとまずここに
Keep up!
ついてこい
Da is leading some Imperial Guards to look for you.
阿大が禁軍を率いて捜索に来ました
They are almost here!
もうすぐよ
Yuanji, lend me the seal of the Household Department.
姉上 少府の印章をお貸しください
No problem.
ええ
She ran away,
逃げられました
after robbing me of the Household Department seal.
私の少府の印章を奪って逃げました
Leave town tonight,
夜のうちに城を出て
and rush to the post house.
すぐに駅へ向かいなさい
Make sure you tell the Heir about the incident in Jiankang
必ず岐王の手が来る前に
before Prince Qi's people arrive.
剣慷の異変を伝えるのです
Got it.
はい
However, now, there must be ambushes
ですが今は四方の城壁に
all around the city walls.
伏兵が潜んでいるはずです
This time, leaving town
この脱出は
will get you in grave danger.
命懸けになります
I alone might not be able
百人相手では
to fight off many soldiers,
勝てずとも
but I can definitely outrun them.
逃げ切る自信はあります
There won't be anyone left for you to use here
ですが私が城を出れば
once I am out of the city.
城内は手薄になります
As for your safety...
その時の世子妃様のご安否が
Don't worry.
案ずるな
Who's there?
誰だ
I'll protect the Heir's Consort.
私が世子妃様をお守りします
You're also a royal Shadow Envoy?
お前も皇家影使か
Not just me.
私だけではない
In Jiankang,
剣慷城内には
there are many others like me,
私のような者が大勢いる
who were ordered
我らはかつて
years ago to protect Crown Prince Wenxi.
文熹太子を守る命を受けましたが
But Crown Prince Wenxi has never called on us.
太子は一度も我らを用いられなかった
He only hopes that we live our lives well.
ただ穏やかに生きることを望んでおられた
Ye Xing?
夜行
Your Highness!
世子様
Prince Jing'an killed Xie Huaigui and was caught
王爺が謝懐帰を殺害し
by the Commandant of Justice on the spot!
廷尉に現行犯で捕らえられました
While being pursued,
追跡のさなか
Prince Jing'an even severely injured the Commandant.
王爺は廷尉に重傷を負わせたとのこと
Prince Qi has ordered
岐王が命を下し
everyone in the mansion to be detained!
王府の者は全員連行されました
What about the Heir's Consort?
世子妃は
He Yuan,
何元
you are not an imperial censor.
そなたは御史ではない
It is not your duty to remonstrate.
諫言は役目ではないぞ
Has Your Highness forgotten about the Northern Expedition?
殿下は北伐の志をお忘れですか
How insolent!
無礼者
Do not forget whose salary you take.
誰の禄を食んでいるか忘れたか
I am completely loyal, and I admonish
二心はございません
for the good of the country.
天下のために諫言を
The Xiao family has been in charge of Beifu for years,
蕭氏は長年 北府を治め
with a distinguished military record and a credit to the nation.
多大な戦功で国に尽くしてきました
I hope Your Highness will investigate the Grand Tutor's death thoroughly,
殿下 何とぞ太傅の件を再調査ください
and not be instigated by Northern Qin
北秦の扇動に乗せられ
to sow discord between Your Highness and the Beifu Army,
殿下と北府軍の仲が裂かれ
thus jeopardizing the Northern Expedition.
北伐の戦機を逃してはなりませぬ
Such clever yet fallacious remarks
巧言令色
have added to your offense.
罪を重ねるか
Strike him 30 times with a cane
棒打ち30回
right here in the court.
この場で執行せよ
Yes.
はっ
Attendants!
者ども
Years ago, when the Capital fell,
かつて上京が陥落した際
countless Ye people were reduced
どれほどの大鄴の民が
to slaves of Northern Qin,
北秦の奴隷となり
living a life worse than that of an animal.
犬畜生にも劣る日々を送ったことか
War has never ceased for 20-odd years.
20年余りも戦乱は続いた
Now, I have arrested Prince Jing'an
今 私が靖安王を捜すのは
not because of the Grand Tutor's death,
太傅の死のためではない
but the purpose of sacrificing a sinful minister's head
罪人の首で
to the upcoming Northern Expedition.
北伐の旗印とするのだ
I no longer care if you lot
そなたらが余の身分を疑おうと
suspect my identity,
もはや気にせぬ
because what I need to do
余がなすべきは
is let my determination be seen by all in the world.
天下に余の覚悟を示すことだ
Your Highness, a secret report from the Brocade Guard.
殿下 錦衣使より密書が
Announce it.
読め
Read it out aloud before the top scholar of the spring exam.
春試の首席の前で大声で読むのだ
Yes.
はっ
Beacon fires were lit and an urgent message came from afar:
狼煙による急報
A Black Cavalry squad of the Beifu Army
北府の黒騎が一隊
is traveling day and night,
昼夜を問わず進軍
heading straight for Jiankang.
剣慷へ直進
They are moving so fast
その勢いは速く
that they are now less than 20 li from Xuan River.
玄水まで二十里足らず
The squad is about to cross the river,
渡河は目前
so prepare defenses now.
速やかに防備を
Let there be no oversight.
万全を期されたし
Did you hear that?
聞こえたか
Xiao Wuyi has deployed a troop back.
蕭無衣が兵を率いて戻った
Since the Beifu Reform began,
北府の改制後
unless ordered by the imperial government,
中枢の勅旨なくして
local garrison troops cannot leave their stations.
守備兵は駐屯地を離れられぬ
This is a military rule set by Xiao Wuyi himself,
これは蕭無衣が自ら定めた軍規
yet he broke it.
それを自ら破ったのだ
Do you still want to plead for him?
それでもなお やつをかばうか
Take this secret report
この密書を手に取り
and have a good look at it yourself!
己の目でよく見よ
-I want to get out of here! -There, there.
もういい 外に出る
-Don't cry. -I want to get out!
泣かないで 外に出たいの
I want to get out of this place!
外に出るの
Mom, I want to get out of here!
母上 外に出ます
Don't be afraid. Eat it.
怖がらないで 食べなさい
Any findings?
どうだ
Ye Xing just sent over a message.
先ほど夜行より知らせが
The Black Cavalry troop can't be reached after crossing Xuan River.
黒騎は玄水を渡った後 消息を絶ちました
The Heir's journey back to the Capital must be dangerous.
世子が今回 京に戻れば血の雨が降るでしょう
If success can't be guaranteed,
確たる勝算がないのなら
maybe we should
いっそ
head back to the Northern Border.
我々は先に北境へ戻りましょう
Back to the Northern Border?
北境へ戻るだと
Then what about Prince Jing'an
では王爺はどうなさる
and Young Master Yao?
若君はどうなるのです
If you're afraid to die,
死ぬのが怖いなら
I'll risk my life.
私が行って命を懸けます
You...
お前
Your Highness.
世子様
They are coming for us.
狙いは我々だ
Mom, I'm scared.
母上 怖いです
Don't be.
大丈夫よ
Where are they?
人は
Still haven't
まだ
found Xie Jiayu?
謝嘉魚の隠れ家は見つからぬのか
General Da has led the Imperial Guard
阿大将軍が禁軍を率いて
to search the entire Jiankang,
剣慷城の全域を捜索しました
but found no trace of the Heir's Consort.
世子妃の足取りはつかめませんでした
As the Beifu Reform has progressed for two years,
この二年 北府の改制で
the Imperial Guard has taken a brand new look,
禁軍も生まれ変わり
with the ability to seal the city like a drum.
剣慷城は鉄壁と化しました
But Xie Jiayu still
だが謝嘉魚は
managed to disappear under our noses.
まんまと目と鼻の先から消えた
This means Xie Jiayu, Xiao Wuyi,
つまり謝嘉魚にしろ
and even some others
蕭無衣にしろ
know a secret escape route
剣慷城には
in Jiankang that I am unaware of!
余の知らぬ逃げ道がある
It proves that I still don't
つまり この剣慷城は
have complete control over Jiankang!
いまだ余の手に落ちておらぬ
It already happens in a city.
一城にしてこの様
What if it spreads to the whole country?
一国ならばどうだ
Xiao Wuyi is back in Jiankang now, isn't he?
蕭無衣は剣慷に戻ったのだな
Yes.
はい
Have Jing Lan keep a close watch on Xiyue Restaurant
景蘭に西月楼を監視させろ
and the Miraculous Craft.
妙手を見張るのだ
Yes.
はっ
Careful.
ゆっくり
Xi-Xiyue Restaurant...
せ…西月楼
Why is a part missing?
なぜ角が欠けている
This is a Ghost Lamp.
これは百鬼灯と言って
It has a special meaning.
特殊な意味があるんだ
What kind of meaning?
どんな意味だ
Does it send warning signals or what?
まさか 警告の意味でもあるのか
Yes.
そうだ
It does send warning signals.
警告の意味がある
Keep drinking!
さあ 飲もう
Tonight, none of us can go home until we're drunk!
今夜は酔い潰れるまで飲むぞ
Let's drink!
飲もう
Come on, let's go.
行くぞ
This...
これは
Xiao Wuyi is cunning and sly.
蕭無衣は狡猾だ
Even if he's back,
戻ってきたとしても
he won't walk right into the trap by coming here.
わざわざ罠にかかりに ここへは来ない
So we're in the Court of Judicial Review now.
大理寺に入ったのか
This is hardly an accomplishment.
大理寺に入ることなど大したことではない
Are Prince Jing'an, Princess Jing'an,
王爺様と王妃様 それに蕭堯が
and Xiao Yao all in there?
中にいます
Yaoyao,
夭夭ちゃん
it's time to go home.
帰る時間よ
You figured I'd come here.
私がここへ来ると読んでいたか
I also figured you'd use Xiao Wuyi
蕭無衣さんをおとりに
to create a diversion.
陽動をかけることもお見通しだ
What, aren't you afraid I'd catch him?
どうだ 私に捕まるのが怖くないとでも
You wouldn't be able to.
彼を捕らえられはしない
Right.
ああ
I did fail to catch him.
捕らえ損ねて
He ended up running away.
逃がしてしまった
Nonetheless,
だが
I guessed you'd take this chance to come rescue his family out of prison.
この機に乗じて脱獄させに来ることも読んでいた
Run!
早く行け
Let's go, Madam Liu.
早く 柳女官様
Xiao Wuyi, why did you come here?
蕭無衣 何しに来た
I had to, or you can't escape.
俺が来なければ 逃げられなかったぞ
Xiao Wuyi,
蕭無衣
release His Highness!
殿下をお放しなさい
is this what you call
これがそなたの言う
"being devoted to the country"?
天下のためか
Li Mao, you clearly went way out of line.
李茂 そちらがあまりに非道だ
You were perfectly aware
私の父上が
that my father was murdered by Northern Qin,
北秦に殺されたと知りながら
yet you still seized on it
それを口実に
to take the power over the Beifu Army
北府の兵権を奪い
and persecute Prince Jing'an's family.
靖安王府を滅ぼそうとは
How can you be so unreasonable?
まだ道理を説く気か
Since when has Jiankang ever been a place
この剣慷でいつから
where being reasonable works?
道理が通用した
The secret passage you just went through
そなたらが通った抜け道や
and the martial masters hidden in the crowd—
人混みに潜む達人が
are you keeping them
今後 余と道理を説くための
so you can reason with me in the future?
手立てか
Xiao Wuyi,
蕭無衣
tomorrow is the day of execution.
明日は処刑の日だ
Even if you can escape death,
そなたは逃げられても
those three
あの３人は
family members of yours will not.
絶対に逃げられん
Li Mao,
李茂
I've been tolerant enough with you.
私はそなたに情けを尽くした
When we meet again,
次に会う時は
I will show you no mercy.
容赦しない
Your Highness!
殿下
No need to go after him.
追う必要はない
With Prince Jing'an and his other family in my hands,
靖安王府の者たちが人質なら
he'll surely hurl himself into the net.
奴は必ず自ら罠にかかる